<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="getting-started" version="5.0"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Getting Started</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>SlipStream™, by SixSq, is a framework for the automatic deployment
    and testing of n-tier and distributed software systems. It makes extensive
    use of cloud computing technologies to provide dynamic near-production
    environments for realistic runtime creation of systems, permitting
    software stakeholders to assert their ability to release the software into
    production on a continuous basis. SlipStream™ relies on virtualization for
    deploying machines and uses a cloud computing back-end to manage the
    life-cycle of virtual images. SlipStream™ can use several cloud backends,
    simultaneously. Please refer to the SixSq website for the list of
    supported clouds. For this tutorial, we assume that you are using
    a <link xlink:href="http://stratuslab.eu">StratusLab</link> cloud.
    Therefore, if you are using a different cloud, the configuration 
    parameters might be slightly different.  SlipStream
    will continue to support more cloud back-ends, as needed and
    requested.</para>

    <para>SlipStream™ is available as public
	<link xlink:href="http://slipstream.sixsq.com">hosted service</link>, our
	hosted service supports a number of clouds. Before you can
    successfully use these clouds, you will need to have valid accounts with
    them.</para>

    <para>This tutorial document is composed of several tutorials of
    increasing complexity, designed to get you started on SlipStream™ as fast
    and simply as possible. The first <link
    linkend="chap-client-server">Simple Client/Server Tutorial</link> uses the
    Apache2 web server to demonstrate a "hello world" of distributed system
    tests using SlipStream™. In this first tutorial, we show you how to use
    existing base images to create a deployment to test a simple client/server
    pair running on two different virtual machines in the cloud.</para>

    <para>Reusing the first tutorial, we then move to a slightly more complex
    scenario where we show you how with a few button clicks the first tutorial
    can be turned into a powerful performance system test. This second case
    deploys several clients in parallel to show how to produce increased load
    on the web server.</para>

    <!--

    <para>Another tutorial, also building from the first <link
    linkend="chap-client-server">Simple Client/Server Tutorial</link>, shows
    how a disk image can be used for data intensive tests and when permanent
    storage is required. In that tutorial, you will define a disk image, which
    is a persistent storage mechanism, which can be attached to different
    machine images. This is useful when complex or large datasets are required
    to perform tests or initialise services, without having to 'bake' into
    each image a large dataset, in other words decoupling data from machine
    images.</para>

    -->

    <!--<para>We conclude with a real life tutorial, where we show you how we at
    SixSq are using SlipStream™ ourselves to build and test SlipStream™. In
    this last tutorial, we describe the steps we use to build one of the main
    components of SlipStream™, namely the orchestrator.</para>

    -->

    <para>We execute the tutorials in this document daily to make sure that
    the fundamentals of these tutorials are sound. However, if you experience
    problems going through these tutorials, you'll find a special appendix to
    this document with troubleshooting tips. If you think that any of these
    tutorials are not clear, confusing, missing insights or could simply be
    made better, please help us improving them by sending your feedback to
    <email>support@sixsq.com</email>.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Tutorial Solutions</title>

    <para>You can find the solutions to the SlipStream™ tutorials on the
    server in the <filename>Public/Tutorials</filename> project area. All of
    the required projects are publicly readable, you therefore only need a
    standard SlipStream™ account to view them.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Key Concepts</title>

    <para>Before we start the tutorial, here are a few important SlipStream™
    concepts that will come up often. SlipStream™ is accessed via a web
    application. SixSq runs a public <link
    xlink:href="http://slipstream.sixsq.com/">SlipStream™ hosted service</link>.
	Your organization may run it's own SlipStream™ service;
    if so, contact your administrator to find the address of the server. If
    you have your own SlipStream™ instance and you want to use it for this
    tutorial, please make sure that your instance of SlipStream™ includes the
    Tutorial SlipStream™ Projects, which ships with the product by
    default.</para>

    <!--

    <para>By default, SlipStream™ runs in protected mode and can only be
    accessed using the secure HTTPS protocol. This is important in order to
    protect your personal credentials and any sensitive information that may
    be storing in your definition and execution procedures.</para>

    -->

    <para>Metadata about your images and deployments are organized into
    projects in SlipStream™. Each project consists of a number of
    modules. The modules may be <emphasis>Project</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>Machine Image</emphasis> or <emphasis>Deployment</emphasis>
    modules. Here is a short description of these module types:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Project</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A container of modules used to provide logical grouping. A
          project may contain other projects allowing a hierarchical
          organization for large projects.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Machine image</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A module that contains information about machine images,
          including cloud specific unique identifier and/or recipes to create
          the machine image. The recipe information consists of a set of
          packages to install and a script for configuring the machine. Unique
          identifiers are specific to the corresponding cloud they belong to.
          This module also includes input/output parameters such that the
          machine can be synchronized as part of a deployment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <!--

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Disk image</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A module that contains data that can be reused during tests
          and machine image build and execution. This is implemented with the
          Amazon's Elastic Block Service (EBS) and will appear to virtual
          machines as a mounted disk.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      -->

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deployment</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>A module that describes nodes to which machine images are
          associated, as well as synchronization and coordination between
          these.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The web interface allows the parameters for each of these modules to
    be defined, edited, versioned and saved.</para>

    <para>We also have three main workflows in SlipStream™: <emphasis>Image
    Creation</emphasis> and <emphasis>Deployment</emphasis>. Here is a short
    explanation of what they are:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Image Creation</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Creation of a new machine image at the cloud service level,
          such that it can be reused in deployments. This means that
          SlipStream™ instantiates a reference (i.e. already existing) image,
          from which it will add software and configuration, before saving it
          as a new image for further reuse.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Deployment Execution (or Run)</term>

        <listitem>
          <para>Deployment of several machines together, synchronizing their
          setup such that the software in each machine fires in the right
          order, automatically.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

	<para>It is also possible to run a single image, without deployment
	support, for convenience.</para>

    <para>These terms will be referred to throughout this document.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Access Control</title>

	<para>Access control can be defined for each module in SlipStream™.
	Further, three levels of control are available: 
	<emphasis>User</emphasis>, <emphasis>Group</emphasis> and
	<emphasis>Public</emphasis>.  For each level, different actions can
	be granted (e.g. read, execute). Groups are dynamically defined, as
	a simple list of users and can be inherited.
	</para>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>User Setup</title>

    <para>SlipStream™ is a secure web application requiring a personal
    account. To register for an account, fill in the <link
    xlink:href="http://slipstream.sixsq.com/register">registration
    form</link>. Make sure you provide a valid email address as it will be
    used to validate your account. Once you've received the email, hit the
    confirmation link to activate your account. From that point-on, you are
    good to go on SlipStream™.</para>

    <!-- <para>By default, on the public hosted service, SlipStream™ is
	configured to use the StratusLab
    reference cloud service for "cloud" resources. In order to build images
    and execute deployments, you must have an <link
    xlink:href="http://stratuslab.eu/">StratusLab account</link> and you must
    fill your SlipStream™ profile with your StratusLab username and password.
    The simplest way to request a StratusLab account is to access the 
	StratusLab <link xlink:href="http://register.stratuslab.eu:8444">registration
	page</link>. SlipStream™ supports several other cloud services, if you
	prefer to use another cloud service, simply change the default in your
	user configuration, and provide the corresponding credentials.</para> -->
	
    <para>To start with SlipStream™, on the welcome page, click on Start or
    the Start button, or the login
    link at the top right of the screen. Once logged in, go to you account.
    Once there, click the Edit button and select the "Properties" tab. Each
    available cloud has a corresponding section (see the comments
    next to the fields for guidance). Configure each cloud section you
    plan to use and save changes. Now you should be good to go!</para>

  </section>
</chapter>
