<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>SlipStream™ captures information about machine images and system
  deployments. It provides a mechanism for automatically deploying system
  configurations and running a battery of tests against the deployed
  configuration. Benefits of the system include:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Explicit capture of machine and system configuration, reducing the
      risk of information loss from personnel changes.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Improved reproducibility via defined machine and deployment
      "recipes".</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Reduced effort by handling machine deployment and clean up
      automatically.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
      <para>Better team cohesion and communication by making full deployment
      accessible to everyone in software production team.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Users (software developers, integrators, testers, and deployment
  experts) interact with SlipStream™ via a web interface. They can define
  their machine images system deployments via the web interface. Once a
  deployment is defined, the user can launch an instance of the deployment,
  run tests against it (either automatically or manually), and then collect
  the test results.</para>

  <para>The SlipStream™ system consists of four components: a server, a
  client, a database, and a "cloud". The server acts as the central point of
  the system, providing the web interface to users and acting as the contact
  point for resources running in the cloud. The client interface, used
  principally in machine images running in the cloud, permits command line and
  programmatic access to the server. A database stores all of the metadata
  related to the machine images and deployments. The "cloud" contains
  computing and storage resources that are used to instantiate dynamically
  system deployments.</para>
</chapter>
