<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Setting Up Database</title>

  <para>The metadata describing machine and deployment configurations are
  stored in a relational database. SlipStream™ uses standard JDBC bindings to
  access the database, so the server should work with any database that
  provides a JDBC driver. In practice, the system is regularly tested with
  MySQL and Derby; hence, those are the recommended databases to use.</para>

  <section>
    <title>MySQL</title>

    <para>You should use MySQL 5.0 or later. Once the server has been
    installed and configured, create a database for SlipStream™. You must also
    create a user that has full rights to administer that database. Ensure
    that the user is allowed to access the database from the SlipStream™
    server (localhost if the database is running on the same machine as the
    server).</para>

    <para>You must download the JDBC drivers corresponding to the MySQL
    version that your running. Ensure that those drivers are in the CLASSPATH
    when starting the SlipStream™ server.</para>

    <para>Use the <filename>slipstream-schema.sql</filename> file in the
    distribution to setup the tables necessary for the server.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Derby</title>

    <para>The Derby database can either be used as a stand-alone server or as
    an embedded server. In either case, create the database for the
    SlipStream™ server. Create the database with a username and password. If
    running the server as an embedded server, the database must clearly reside
    on the same machine as the server. A stand-alone server can be deployed on
    a separate machine if desired.</para>

    <para>The Derby database and JDBC driver are distributed with the
    SlipStream™ distribution.</para>

    <para>Use the <filename>slipstream-schema.sql</filename> file in the
    distribution to setup the tables necessary for the server.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
