<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Installation</title>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>The system has been designed to have as few requirements as
    possible. Nonetheless, there are some prerequisites for successfully
    running SlipStream™. The server must have:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Java 6 or later installed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A publicly accessible network address.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Either a commercial or self-signed certificate for SSL.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Access to a database that has a JDBC driver.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Any firewall around the server must allow access to port 443 (or
        configured port) on the server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The clients running within the cloud must have:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Python 2.5 installed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>SlipStream™ client software installed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Resources in the cloud must have port 22 accessible and be able
        to contact the SlipStream™ server.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>SlipStream™ currently uses Amazon Web Services as the provider of
    cloud resources. Each user must have valid Amazon credentials in order to
    use the system. Deployments are submitted with the user's credentials and
    usage is charged directly to the user.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment Models</title>

    <para>There are a couple of deployment models for the system: Standalone
    and Servlet. Of the two models, the easier to setup and configure is the
    "Standalone" server. This uses the standard RESTlet HTTP(S) server and
    client. If the Derby database is used with the Standalone server, no
    additional software needs to be downloaded.</para>

    <para>The Servlet model is a bit more complicated, but may be desired to
    take advantage of an existing servlet infrastructure. Although the server
    should work with any Servlet container, we routinely test the system with
    Tomcat and recommend using that.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Distributions</title>

    <para>SixSq Sàrl provides a central server for evaluation of the service
    and for limited use of the system. Send an email to
    <email>slipstream-support@sixsq.com</email> to request an account on that
    server. To deploy a private server, please send an email to the same
    address indicating that you would like to deploy a private instance. You
    will be contacted about licensing conditions and prices.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Unpacking Distribution</title>

    <para>For the Standalone distribution, unpack the distribution into a
    convenient directory. You can copy the startup script to the appropriate
    area to have the server automatically started when the machine boots.
    </para>

    <para>For the Servlet distribution, unpack the distribution into a
    temporary directory. Take the web archive file and drop this into your
    Tomcat (or other servlet container). Depending on the database that you
    have chosen you may also need to add your database's JDBC driver to the
    Tomcat CLASSPATH.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
