<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>User Account Configuration</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Torque uses standard unix account information to authorize users to
    access the Torque server, to execute jobs on the computing resources, and
    to return job output to the user. Although there are several ways to set
    up the batch system to achieve this, the easiest is to have a common
    account configuration and common file system shared by all of the machines
    in the system. In production, an LDAP server usually provides the account
    configuration and an NFS server, the shared file system.</para>

    <para>To simplify this use case, a common account configuration (including
    SSH keys) will be created by using a common machine image for all of the
    machines in the batch system. This allows the configuration to be done
    once and to avoid having to dynamically copy SSH keys between machines at
    runtime. Use of common machine images is a useful technique for
    distributing a common configuration between machines in a
    deployment.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Creating Machine Image</title>

    <para>To create the base image (named "Cluster_Base_Image") with the
    account configuration, a new machine image is created with the following
    recipe:</para>

    <programlisting>#!/bin/sh -x

# Add a group that will contain all of the users.
GROUP=users
groupadd ${GROUP}

# Loop over the desired user names, creating the account
# and setting up the ssh configuration.
for USERNAME in "userx" "usery" "userz"; do

  # Create the user.  Make sure that the PRIMARY group is
  # 'users'.  This is needed for torque spool areas.
  useradd --create-home -g users ${USERNAME}

  # Setup various locations for the ssh configuration.
  HOME_DIR=/home/${USERNAME}
  SSH_DIR=${HOME_DIR}/.ssh
  KEY_FILE=${SSH_DIR}/id_rsa

  # Remove any existing ssh directory and create it from scratch.
  # This will also remove any ssh keys and configurations.
  if [ -e ${SSH_DIR} ]; then
    rm -Rf ${SSH_DIR}
  fi
  mkdir -p ${SSH_DIR}

  # Generate the key for this account.  (This has NO password.)
  ssh-keygen -t rsa -f ${KEY_FILE} -N ""

  # Generate the authorized key files.
  cp -f ${KEY_FILE}.pub ${SSH_DIR}/authorized_keys
  cp -f ${KEY_FILE}.pub ${SSH_DIR}/authorized_keys2

  # Ensure that all of the files have the correct owner and group.
  chown -R ${USERNAME}:${GROUP} ${SSH_DIR} 

done</programlisting>

    <para>This creates three user accounts (userx, usery, and userz) along
    with new SSH keys without passwords. Once the image has been created, then
    any other image which depends on this will share the given account
    configuration.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
