<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section>
    <title>Torque Batch System</title>

    <para>Torque is an open-source batch system maintained by <link
    xlink:href="http://www.clusterresources.com/">Cluster Resources</link>. As
    for all batch systems, Torque manages a set of distributed computing
    resources allowing multiple users to run jobs (or tasks) on those
    resources. A full batch system deployment contains a server for managing
    job submissions, a set of workers for executing the jobs, and one or more
    clients from which users submit jobs.</para>

    <para>All of the modules for this use case can be found in the "Torque"
    project.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Purpose</title>

    <para>The purpose of this use case is to show how SlipStream™ can be used
    to build packages for Torque on a specific operating system and to test
    those packages. This use case will install and configure those packages in
    a variety of deployments, ensuring via a simple job submission that the
    packages function correctly.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Scenarios</title>

    <para>The most complex scenario that we want to test will involve a torque
    server, multiple (3) workers, and multiple (2) clients. The server,
    workers, and clients will all be on separate machines that share a common
    user configuration.</para>

    <para>Rather than starting with the complex scenario, we will work up to
    it starting from a simple, monolithic deployment and gradually increasing
    the complexity. The scenarios that we will treat are:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Monolithic Deployment: A single machine will function as a
        server, worker, and client; the deployment will contain one
        machine.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Separate Worker: A machine will function as a server and a
        client. A separate machine will function as the worker. This
        deployment will contain two machines.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Separate Worker and Client: The server, worker, and client will
        each be on a separate machine. This deployment will contain three
        machines.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Multiple Workers and Clients: The deployment will contain 3
        workers, 2 clients, and 1 server all on separate machines. This
        deployment will contain 6 machines.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To determine that the system is working correctly, a test will
    submit jobs from user accounts on the clients and verify that each job's
    standard error and standard output contain the correct information. The
    same test is used for all of the deployments.</para>

    <para>To ensure that the packages are built correctly for the underlying
    operating system, the Torque packages will be built from sources on the
    base machine image. The generated packages will then be stored in Amazon's
    S3 for later installation on the machines involved in the batch system
    tests.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
