<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Maven Integration</title>

  <section>
    <title>What is Maven?</title>

    <para>Maven is an extensible framework which allows fine control over the
    build and test process while supporting complete automation. Maven's
    repository model is a particular strength, allowing the automatic
    resolution of dependencies and providing a consistent mechanism build
    coordination through the repository. More information about maven can be
    found on the project's website.</para>

    <para>Because of its widespread use, Maven has been integrated into many
    continuous build tools, notably Hudson and Jenkins. Providing integration
    of SlipStream with maven therefore offers the possibility of integrating
    SlipStream actions into a build and test process built around existing
    continuous integration tools.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>SlipStream Archetype</title>

    <para>Maven is capable of generating skeletons of new projects based on
    defined "archetypes". An archetype for a SlipStream module exists and can
    be used to generate a working maven project that runs a given SlipStream
    deployment. To use the archetype, run the following command:</para>

    <programlisting>mvn archetype:generate \
  -DarchetypeArtifactId=slipstream-module \
  -DarchetypeGroupId=com.sixsq.slipstream \
  -DarchetypeVersion=1.0 \
  -Dslipstream-url=http://slipstream.stratuslab.eu \
  -Dslipstream-module=Tutorial/HelloWorld/client_server </programlisting>

    <para>The first three parameters define the archetype to use; they are all
    required. You may check for the latest version of the archetype by
    searching in the maven central repository. The last two parameters are
    optional and if not given, default values will be used.</para>

    <para>When the command above is run, it will prompt for required values
    that have not been specified. In particular, it will ask for a groupId and
    artifactId for the module. These should follow standard maven conventions.
    If the above command finished successfully, then it will have created a
    subdirectory with the same name as the artifactId. You can then descend
    into this subdirectory and perform the usual maven commands:</para>

    <programlisting>$ mvn install</programlisting>

    <para>which will run the given SlipStream module and install the
    deployment's results as build artifacts. By default, the SlipStream
    deployment will be executed during the integration-test phase.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Maven Plugin</title>

    <para>A maven plugin is available from the central maven repository that
    allows users to run a deployment module defined in SlipStream from maven,
    to follow the evolution of the deployment, and to recover the results from
    each node in the deployment. The results are registered as artifacts of
    the maven build and will be uploaded into the defined maven repository if
    the install or deploy phase is executed.</para>

    <para>The simplest method for creating a maven module capable of running a
    SlipStream deployment is to use the archetype defined in the previous
    section. This will create a working skeleton capable of running a given
    SlipStream deployment module.</para>

    <para>To get information about the plugin itself and its parameters, you
    can use maven's help plugin:</para>

    <programlisting>$ mvn help:describe -Dplugin=slipstream -Ddetail</programlisting>

    <para>This will provide a listing of all parameters, their descriptions,
    and their default values (if any).</para>

    <programlisting>...
[INFO] com.sixsq.slipstream:slipstream-maven-plugin:1.0

Name: SlipStream Maven Plugin
Description: Sonatype helps open source projects to set up Maven repositories
  on https://oss.sonatype.org/
Group Id: com.sixsq.slipstream
Artifact Id: slipstream-maven-plugin
Version: 1.0
Goal Prefix: slipstream

This plugin has 1 goal:

slipstream:run-deployment
  Description: runs the specified deployment modules(s), adding the reports
    as project artifacts
  Implementation: com.sixsq.slipstream.SlipStreamMojo
  Language: java
  Bound to phase: integration-test

  Available parameters:

    deploymentModuleNames
      Name(s) of the deployment modules to run. If multiple modules are
      supplied, they will be run sequentially.

    pollIntervalInSeconds (Default: 15)
      Poll interval (in seconds) for checking the deployment status

    slipstreamServerId (Default: slipstream)
      SlipStream server ID used in the settings.xml file. This cannot be empty
      or null. The user's username and password must be available from the
      settings.xml file for this server ID.

    slipstreamServerUrl
      Root URL for the SlipStream server

...

</programlisting>

    <para>The plugin must access the SlipStream server as a valid user,
    consequently you must provide your SlipStream username and password to the
    plugin. This is done through your settings.xml file, so that the
    information does not need to be included in the pom.xml. </para>

    <programlisting>&lt;settings xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/SETTINGS/1.0.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/SETTINGS/1.0.0
                      http://maven.apache.org/xsd/settings-1.0.0.xsd"&gt;
  &lt;localRepository/&gt;
  &lt;interactiveMode/&gt;
  &lt;usePluginRegistry/&gt;
  &lt;offline/&gt;

  &lt;pluginGroups&gt;
    &lt;pluginGroup&gt;com.sixsq.slipstream&lt;/pluginGroup&gt;
  &lt;/pluginGroups&gt;

  &lt;servers&gt;
    &lt;server&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;slipstream&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;username&gt;my_slipstream_username&lt;/username&gt;
      &lt;password&gt;my_slipstream_password&lt;/password&gt;
    &lt;/server&gt;
  &lt;/servers&gt;

  &lt;mirrors/&gt;
  &lt;proxies/&gt;
  &lt;profiles/&gt;
  &lt;activeProfiles/&gt;

&lt;/settings&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The id in the settings.xml file must match the value given for the
    slipstreamServerId parameter. </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
