<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Project Module</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para><emphasis>Projects</emphasis> in SlipStream are similar to
    directories or folders in normal file systems. They basically provide
    grouping. Projects can contain other projects, which are normally used to
    organise all the other metadata modules. Like all items in SlipStream,
    Projects are version controlled and have specific access control
    parameters. By default, Projects are private to their owner, but can be
    made public.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Root Project</title>

    <para>SlipStream follows a <emphasis>shared root project</emphasis> model.
    This means that all projects share the same namespace. This doesn't mean
    that your root project must be public, on the contrary, it simply means
    that its name must be unique with respect to other root projects.
    SlipStream will report an error if you choose a name already used by
    another user.</para>

    <para>To access the Root Project of the public installation, go here:
    <link
    xlink:href="https://slipstream.sixsq.com/module">slipstream.sixsq.com/projects</link>.
    Like most pages in SlipStream, this page requires to login to the
    application. From this page, you will be able to create new projects by
    clicking on the <literal>New Project</literal> link (see <xref
        linkend="fig-new-project">
        .
      </xref>), or view existing projects, that are either public or owned by
    you.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-new-project">
      <title>New Project</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Projects/new-project.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Standard Project</title>

    <para>With the exception of the Root Project described above, which only
    contains a list of projects your user has access to, sub-projects contain
    further information. This information is described in this section.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Viewing Project</title>

      <para>To view a project details, navigate to the project by clicking on
      its parent name from the root project. On the project page, you will
      have access to the <emphasis>Summary</emphasis> tab (<xref
          linkend="fig-project-summary">
          .
        </xref>), selected by default, as well as the
      <emphasis>Authorization</emphasis> tab (<xref
          linkend="fig-project-authorization">
          .
        </xref>), which gives you access to the access control parameters of
      the module.</para>

      <figure xml:id="fig-project-summary">
        <title>Project Summary</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                       fileref="images/Projects/project-summary.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <figure xml:id="fig-project-authorization">
        <title>Project Authorization</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                       fileref="images/Projects/project-authorization.png"
                       format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Editing Project</title>

      <para>To edit your account, navigate to the project by clicking on its
      parent name from the root project. On the desired project page hit the
      <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> button.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Summary</title>

        <para>The default tab for Project module is the
        <emphasis>Summary</emphasis>. On that tab, your can edit general
        information such as description, as well as creating new
        modules.</para>

        <para>To create a new module (e.g. Sub-Project, Machine Image, Disk
        Image, Deployment), press respective button in Modules sections of
        <emphasis>Summary</emphasis> tab (<xref linkend="fig-project-summary">
            .
          </xref>). You will then be redirected to a new page in which you'll
        be able to fill the information corresponding to the new
        module.</para>
      </section>

      <xi:include href="section-tab-authorization.xml" xpointer="element(/1)" />
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
