<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title xml:id="refman-chapter-users">User Profile</title>

  <section>
    <title>Registration</title>

    <para>SlipStream is a secured application, which requires authentication.
    New users must create an account, following a simple online registration
    process. To create an account select the <emphasis>login</emphasis> link
    at the top right corner of any SlipStream page. On the login page, click
    on the <emphasis>Register</emphasis> link.</para>

    <para>On the registration page, fill all the required fields, identified
    with a star (*). You also need to read and accept the terms of the
    service. Finally, click on the <emphasis>Register</emphasis> button to
    trigger the registration process. Once your request has been accepted by
    the SlipStream administrator, you will receive a confirmation email with a
    link to activate your account. Once the account is activated, you will be
    able to login and start using SlipStream.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Login</title>

    <para>Once you have an active account, you can login to SlipStream. From
    the main SlipStream page, either select the <emphasis>login</emphasis>
    link at the top right corner of the page, or simply select the
    <emphasis>Start</emphasis> link or the corresponding icon on its left. You
    will then be directed to the <emphasis>login</emphasis> page. To login,
    enter your user name and password in the appropriate fields and hit the
    <emphasis>Log in</emphasis> button. Once you're logged in, you will see
    your user name displayed at the top right of all SlipStream pages, as well
    as a <emphasis>logout</emphasis> link.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Viewing Your Account</title>

    <para>To view your account details, login and go to your account page by
    clicking on your user name at the top right of any SlipStream page. On
    that page, you will have access to the <emphasis>Summary</emphasis> tab,
    selected by default, as well as the <emphasis>Properties</emphasis> tab,
    if you have defined any properties previously.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="refman-chapter-users-sec-edit-account">
    <title>Editing Your Account</title>

    <para>To edit your account, login and go to your account page by clicking
    on your user name at the top right of any SlipStream page. On that page
    hit the <emphasis>Edit</emphasis> button.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Summary</title>

      <para>The default tab for the user account is the
      <emphasis>Summary</emphasis>. On that tab, your can edit general
      information such as name and affiliation, as well as email and password.
      If you are granted super user role, you turn your account into a normal
      user by de-selecting the corresponding check-box.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Properties</title>

      <para>The <emphasis>Properties</emphasis> tab as shown on <xref
          linkend="fig-user-properties">
           . 
        </xref> is composed of several groups.</para>

      <figure xml:id="fig-user-properties">
        <title>User Properties</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                       fileref="images/User/user-properties.png" format="PNG"></imagedata>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <section xml:id="chap-user-profile-sec-exec-params">
        <title>Execution Parameters</title>

        <para>This group lets you to control the execution of your builds and
        deployments:</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>On error run forever</term>

            <listitem>
              <para xml:id="on_error_run_forever">When ticked, if the
              deployment execution fails, let all the virtual machines of this
              execution run forever. This is useful for troubleshooting
              failing deployments (see Reference Manual for details). Please
              note that with this option, all failing deployments will run
              forever, which means you have to terminate the virtual machines
              manually.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>On success run forever</term>

            <listitem>
              <para xml:id="on_success_run_forever">When ticked, if the
              deployment succeeds, let all the virtual machines of this
              execution run forever. This is useful when using SlipStream as a
              production deployment engine, or to further test deployed
              systems. With this option, the SlipStream Orchestrator will
              shutdown at the end of the successful deployment, only leaving
              the nodes running. Please note that with this option, all
              successful deployments will run forever, which means you have to
              terminate the virtual machines manually.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>General timeout</term>

            <listitem>
              <para xml:id="general_timeout">This parameter controls the
              maximum time SlipStream will wait for during the execution of
              builds and deployments. This parameter also controls how long
              will blocking reads will wait before they timeout. Make sure to
              adjust this parameter if you build long running machine or disk
              images, as well as deployments.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Cloud Properties</title>

        <para>SlipStream uses a cloud infrastructure to build machine and disk
        images, as well as to deploy your systems. Your account must be
        configured with your cloud provider's credential, such that SlipStream
        can use these credentials on your behalf.</para>

        <para><emphasis role="bold">StratusLab Properties</emphasis></para>

        <para>The following properties are specific to StratusLab type
        credentials.</para>

        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term>StratusLab Endpoint (required to submit to
            StratusLab)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This is the endpoint to a private StratusLab cloud
              deployment. Usually this is just a hostname of the cloud
              front-end for which the the user was granted access via
              StratusLab Username/Password. This field is required to submit
              to StratusLab.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>StratusLab Username (required to submit to
            StratusLab)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This field is required to submit to StratusLab.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>StratusLab Password (required to submit to
            StratusLab)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This field is required to submit to StratusLab.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Marketplace Endpoint (required to submit to StratusLab and
            build images)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>In StratusLab all images are referenced by IDs. StratusLab
              Marketplace is a searchable collection virtual machine images
              identified by the image IDs. This field is required to submit to
              StratusLab and build images.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>AppRepo Endpoint (required to build images)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>In StratusLab, images (appliances) physically are stored
              on the web and accessible via http/ftp protocol. Appliance
              Repository (AppRepo) Endpoint is URI pointing to a server
              capable of storing appliances. This field is required to build
              images.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>AppRepo Username (required to build images)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This field is required to build images.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>AppRepo Password (required to build images)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>This field is required to build images.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term>Ssh PublicKey (required to submit to StratusLab; optional to
            build images)</term>

            <listitem>
              <para>SSH public key(s) (new-line separated list of keys is
              possible). At an image boot time, during the process of
              contexualization the key(s) will be placed in a respective
              location to allow you successive passwordless login to the
              running image instance. This field is required to submit to
              StratusLab and optional to build images.</para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <!--
        <para><emphasis role='bold'>Amazon Properties</emphasis></para>
  
        <para>The following properties are specific to Amazon's type 
        credentials.</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Access id (required to submit to EC2)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This id can be found on the Amazon user's page
            (aws.amazon.com) under <emphasis>Your Account -&gt; Access
            Identifiers</emphasis>. You will find the id under <emphasis>Your
            Access Key ID</emphasis>. It's a 20 characters alpha numerical
            string. This field is required to submit to EC2.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Secret key (required to submit to EC2)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This key can be found on the Amazon user's page
            (aws.amazon.com) under <emphasis>Your Account -&gt; Access
            Identifiers</emphasis>. You will find the id by clicking on the
            <emphasis>+ Show</emphasis> link under <emphasis>Your Secret
            Access Key</emphasis>. It's a 40 characters string, including
            characters such as '/' and '+'. This field is required to submit
            to EC2.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Account number (required to build AMIs) </term>

          <listitem>
            <para>This id can be found on the Amazon user's page
            (aws.amazon.com) under <emphasis>Your Account</emphasis>. You will
            find the Account Number at the top right of that frame. This field
            is required to build Amazon Machine Images (AMI).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Certificate PEM file (required to build AMIs) </term>

          <listitem>
            <para />
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Private PEM file (required to build AMIs) </term>

          <listitem>
            <para />
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Keypair name (required to build AMIs) </term>

          <listitem>
            <para />
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Private key of keypair (required to build AMIs) </term>

          <listitem>
            <para />
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>Security Group (required to build AMIs)</term>

          <listitem>
            <para />
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist> 
-->
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
