<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Image Boot-up Sequence</title>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>In this chapter, we describe the boot-up sequence that takes place
    on SlipStream™ instrumented images. We take great care in minimizing the
    intrusion our instrumentation our tools has on the normal behaviour of the
    image, in order to ensure that the SlipStream™ instrumented images behave
    as closely as possible to the normal deployment sequence you expect when
    deploying your production system.</para>

    <para>We first describe the boot-up sequence for Linux type systems. This
    will be followed in future releases of SlipStream™ by Microsoft Windows
    and Sun Microsystem's OpenSolaris.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Linux Instrumentation</title>

    <para>rc.local...</para>

    <para></para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment Execution Sequence</title>

    <para>This section describes the different stages each deployment goes
    through.<orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Initialisation</para>

          <para>During this execution phase, all machine boot-up and their
          hostname is published to the SlipStream™ information specific to
          this deployment instance. Once all machines have reached this stage,
          the sequence execution resumes with the execution of the
          <command>execute</command> target (if present).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Finalisation</para>

          <para>Once the execute target has returned, whether with a zero or
          none-zero return code, each machine waits to all machines to have
          reached this stage. Once this final stage is reached, the
          <command>report</command> target is executed on all machines. This
          is the time to gather and compile the required information and a
          report bundle is uploaded to the SlipStream™ server for later
          viewing by the user. Once all machines have reached this step, we
          then conclude with the last stage.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Termination</para>

          <para>This last stage informs the SlipStream™ orchestrator that the
          deployment has reached its end and the machines can be shutdown and
          released. The final status of the execution is set (i.e. Finished,
          Failed, Aborted), depending on the execution of the
          deployment.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>You can follow the execution of the deployment by
    monitoring the <command>exec.status</command> execution property on the
    execution web-page.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
