<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
         xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:db="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section xml:id="introdution-overview">
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>SlipStream lets you deploy multi-tier systems in a near production
    environment automatically, such that you can test your system under a
    variety of conditions, in a continuous fashion and without having to
    manage your own infrastructure. This document gives you an overview of the
    functionality of SlipStream. This document is the companion of the
    SlipStream Tutorial document, which presents SlipStream using a series of
    specific examples. We suggest you work with both documents to get up to
    speed quickly. You can also use the SlipStream mailing list at the
    address: slipstream-support@sixsq.com, if you have any questions.</para>

    <para>The SlipStream application has two main workflows: <emphasis>Image
    Creation</emphasis> and <emphasis>Deployment</emphasis>. Lets review these
    two workflows. The <emphasis>Deployment</emphasis> workflow lets you
    deploy several virtual machines together, as part of a consistent system.
    For example, you can deploy a 3-tier system, composed of a client, a
    server and a database, all running on different machines. You can also
    vary the number of machines running clients, servers and databases, since
    they are parameterised in SlipStream, which gives you great flexibility to
    explore different deployment models in a few simple button clicks.</para>

    <para>The underlying cloud environment that SlipStream targets cannot
    predict hostnames or IP addresses. This is a common trait of
    <emphasis>Infrastructure as a Service</emphasis> (IaaS) type clouds. To
    work around this limitation, SlipStream provides a simple messaging API
    that can be used to such that virtual machines can find each other (e.g.
    the server will need to know what database's hostname to connect to, and
    similarly, the client will need to be told what's the server's hostname).
    We describe this API in section <xref
        linkend="chap-client-command-reference">
         . 
      </xref> and you will find examples usage of this API in the tutorial
    document mentioned above.</para>

    <para>The building blocks of a deployment are machine images (i.e. virtual
    images), which can also include disk images (i.e. mountable persistent
    storage for machine images). The creation of these building blocks is
    performed using the <emphasis>Image Creation</emphasis> workflow. We give
    a high-level description of this workflow in the next section, with
    further details in section <xref linkend="chap-machine-image-module">
         . 
      </xref>.</para>

    <para>Users can follow the execution of an image creation or a deployment
    using the SlipStream dashboard, which provides a graphical representation
    of execution. The dashboard represents each deployed virtual machine,
    including its current state and custom information if provided. <!-- This feature is described in section XXX. -->
    <!-- TODO: describe this feature! --> At the end of all execution, a
    consolidated report is made available to the user, including detailed log
    files, if configured, to review the execution.</para>

    <para>We also invite you to read the Best Practice (<xref
        linkend="chap-best-practices">
         . 
      </xref>) chapter, which provides tips and tricks for troubleshooting and
    debugging executions. These best practices take advantage of the fact that
    since we're using virtual machines and a cloud environment, we can
    interrupt the execution of a deployment or a machine image creation, log
    into the offending machine and execute by hand part or all of the
    workflow. This way, you fix problems very quickly and bring the required
    changes back to SlipStream via the user interface, without spending time
    in trial and error experiments.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Image Creation</title>

    <para>Before you can deploy your system in SlipStream, you'll need machine
    images, containing the different tiers you want to deploy. Machine images
    in SlipStream are simply virtual machine images, with a simple
    modification to their boot sequence. You can use already registered
    virtual machines in the cloud environment that your SlipStream
    installation targets (e.g. StratusLab service (via Marketplace image ID)
    or Amazon's EC2 for the public service), or you can create your own.
    Please refer to the cloud providers documentation for creating new base
    virtual images if you don't want to or can't start with existing
    ones.</para>

    <para>The public SlipStream service targets StratusLab and Amazon's EC2
    cloud services. StratusLab (via Marketplace) and Amazon already provide a
    rich set of base images.</para>

    <!--     Some have already been upgraded to work out of the box for SlipStream. We call these images
    <emphasis>stock images</emphasis>. You'll find public stock images in the
    <literal
    xlink:href="https://slipstream.sixsq.com/projects/Public">Public</literal>
    project in SlipStream.
 -->

    <para><xref linkend="fig-image-creation-workflow">
         . 
      </xref> shows the different steps you can follow to create images. You
    can start from a plain image (as in point 1). In this case you will have
    to create a new machine image, referencing the plain image you want to
    base your image on, and provide a <literal>pre-recipe</literal> script.
    This pre-recipe script installs the SlipStream client dependencies onto
    the plain image <!-- (see xxx for details) -->. Once you've built this
    image, you'll have a new stock image (as shown on point 4), which you can
    further customise. If you start from a stock image (point 2), which is the
    fastest and easiest way to go, you can then provide a list of packages to
    install (a.k.a. apt/yum for Linux based machines) and/or a recipe script.
    This will install and configure your machine such that it can be (re)used
    for further customisation (as in point 3) and/or used in an execution, as
    part of a real deployment (point 5).</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-image-creation-workflow">
      <title>Image creation workflow diagram</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/image-creation-workflow-landscape.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/image-creation-workflow-landscape.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para linkend="fig-machine-image-inheritance">As mentioned above, machine
    images can be inherited, as shown on <xref
        linkend="fig-machine-image-inheritance">
         . 
      </xref>. The inheritance mechanism is implemented using reference <!-- (see xxx for details) -->.
    Note that while parameters and properties are inherited, scripts (i.e.
    pre-recipes, recipe, execute and report) and packages are not
    inherited.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-machine-image-inheritance">
      <title>Machine image inheritance</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/machine-image-inheritance.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/machine-image-inheritance.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When creating a machine image, the SlipStream Server starts a
    dedicated virtual machine called an Orchestrator. This is illustrated in
    <xref linkend="fig-image-creation-deployment-model">
         . 
      </xref>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-image-creation-deployment-model">
      <title>Image creation deployment model</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/image-creation-deployment-model.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/image-creation-deployment-model.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Looking at the user interface for a machine image, you'll see that
    we can also define an <emphasis>deployment scripts</emphasis>. These are
    scripts that will be executed during the execution of a machine image,
    every time the machine boots as part of a deployment. We'll look at these
    scripts in the next section.</para>

    <para>Now that we've looked at the highlights of the image creation
    workflow, we'll look at how to combine machine images into a deployment
    model that can be executed to mimic a near-production multi-tier software
    system deployment.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Deployment</title>

    <para>Deployments in SlipStream refers to the launch of a set of virtual
    machines, as part of a coherent software system. We already mentioned the
    example of a client/server/database 3-tier architecture. In this section
    we give an overview of what a deployment is made of and how to take
    advantage of the synchronisation feature SlipStream offers for controlling
    the deployment of inter-dependent machines.</para>

    <para linkend="fig-deployment-deployment-model">In the previous section,
    we briefly introduced the image creation model. For
    <emphasis>deployment</emphasis>s, a similar model exists, as illustrated
    in <xref linkend="fig-deployment-deployment-model">
         . 
      </xref>. The Orchestrator pattern is also used to control the
    instantiation of the virtual machines that as described in the deployment
    model the user wants to execute. In this diagram, the orchestrator
    instantiates three virtual machines called: <emphasis>Node 1</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>Node i</emphasis> and <emphasis>Node N</emphasis>.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-deployment-deployment-model">
      <title>Deployment Model</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-deployment-model.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-deployment-model.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para><xref linkend="fig-deployment-deployment-model">
         . 
      </xref> introduces the concept of <emphasis>node</emphasis>, which is a
    terminology used by SlipStream to associate machine image metadata with
    real virtual machine instances. Section <xref
        linkend="chap-deployment-module">
         . 
      </xref> provides further details on the definition of deployments. For
    now, what's important to understand is that machine images, which can be
    generic units of reuse, can be combined, shared and reused in flexible
    ways between different deployments. For example, the same machine images
    (with or without Disk Images attached) can be combine together using
    different deployment models, such that they can form the basis for a
    simple functional test, end-to-end system test. Further, increasing the
    number of nodes can turn a basic deployment into a powerful performance or
    stress test. For example, you could use this feature to deploy and test
    the same system with a range of back-end databases, to verify the the
    system behaves correctly for all back-ends, automatically, without having
    to deal with the manual work of deploying and maintaining several back-end
    installations in your infrastructure.</para>

    <para>The following figure (<xref
        linkend="fig-deployment-sequence-diagram">
         . 
      </xref>) show the high-level sequence diagram of a deployment. The
    SlipStream Server launches a dedicated SlipStream Orchestrator, a
    dedicated virtual machine for the execution of the deployment. The
    orchestrator analysis the deployment model and launches the required nodes
    (instances of machine images) and coordinates them. This coordination
    includes a few rendezvous points during the deployment for each node. This
    is described in further details a little later in this section. As
    illustrated in <xref linkend="fig-deployment-sequence-diagram">
         . 
      </xref>, during the execution of each node, the SlipStream client
    executes a set of user scripts. These scripts are:
    <emphasis>execute</emphasis> and <emphasis>report</emphasis>. The execute
    script is there to call the normal business logic for this node, while the
    report scripts responsibility is to gather all the logs and other
    important files and sources of information to be added to the execution
    report. Once the execution scripts have run and all the reports have been
    compiled and sent back to the SlipStream Server, the orchestrator normally
    terminates the virtual machines.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-deployment-sequence-diagram">
      <title>Deployment Sequence Diagram</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-sequence-diagram.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-sequence-diagram.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>We already described the limitation that cloud environments have in
    terms of not being able to predict IP addresses and hostnames. Further,
    bootstrapping the deployment of a system on pristine resources is often a
    challenge, since often software services are not design to be deployed
    from scratch automatically. SlipStream offers a simple, yet efficient and
    non-intrusive, mechanism to bootstrap the deployment process of virtual
    machines, as well as providing a synchronisation mechanism (a.k.a
    distributed semaphore-like logic) to control the way the machines come to
    life, including services and their configuration. <xref
        linkend="fig-deployment-deployment-model">
         . 
      </xref> is a high level sequence diagram showing how the synchronisation
    API is used such that the <literal>Node 1</literal> waits for a value set
    by <literal>Node 2</literal>. In this example, the execute script runs
    until it hits a synchronisation point (using either the SlipStream
    command-line client or Python API). At this point, the script blocks,
    waiting for a key to be set. Once <literal>Node 2</literal> sets the key,
    giving it an optional value, the blocked <literal>Node 1</literal> script
    resumes, using the value associated with the key if necessary. While this
    synchronisation mechanism allows simple key/value data exchange between
    nodes (i.e. machine image instances) it is often used as a semaphore
    mechanism for synchronization.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-deployment-synchronisation">
      <title>Deployment Synchronisation</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-synchronisation.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-synchronisation.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Deployments go through a simple set of states, as described in <xref
        linkend="fig-deployment-sequence">
         . 
      </xref>. In that figure, states illustrated with a dotted lined boxes
    correspond to states that are internal to SlipStream while boxes with a
    solid line represent optional states where user scripts can be executed,
    if defined.</para>

    <figure xml:id="fig-deployment-sequence">
      <title>Deployment Sequence</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-state-diagram-landscape.png"
                     format="PNG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>

        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata align="center" contentwidth="14cm"
                     fileref="images/Workflows/deployment-state-diagram-landscape.svg"
                     format="SVG"></imagedata>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>It is worth noting that each virtual machine during a deployment
    execution goes through these states, whether a failure is detected during
    the execution or not. Further, the SlipStream client will force a
    synchronisation point at different points on the sequence. These
    synchronisation points are the following:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>After <emphasis>Initialize</emphasis>: allows each machine to
        have completed its boot sequence before the transition to the
        <emphasis>Execute</emphasis> state is allowed.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>After <emphasis>Execute</emphasis>: ensures that the execution
        has completed before the <emphasis>Report</emphasis> scripts is
        executed. This is important such that the report includes all the
        actions that have taken place during the <emphasis>Execute</emphasis>
        state.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Users can also instruct SlipStream to let the virtual machines
    running if an error was detected during the deployment, or on the
    contrary, if the deployment execution was successful. For further details
    on these option, refer to section <xref
        linkend="chap-user-profile-sec-exec-params">
         . 
      </xref>.</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
